Shin Sapporo Junior High School
Shin Sapporo High School
Hachiken, you're not
gonna join any clubs?
八軒は何か部活やらねーの？
Nope... I'm not good at sports, anyway.
うん…。
俺　スポーツ苦手だし
Yeah?
そうなんだ？
Besides, if I joined any clubs,
それに 部活なんてやってたら 勉強　遅れるだろ
I'd fall behind in my studies.
Academic Ability Test Results
But you can focus better
if you do some physical activity.
でもさ たまに体　動かした方が集中力 上がるぜ？
English
Geography
Besides, you'll get a better
evaluation from our school
それに　中高６年間勉強と部活両方頑張りましたって言えば
if you can say that you did well both
in academics and extracurriculars
throughout junior high
and high school.
内申も上がるし
Sorry.
悪い。　俺　塾あるから
I have to go to cram school.
I really want to get into the
best university possible,
少しでも上のランクの大学行きたいから
Don't budge on
your top choice!
so I gotta pass on the
whole club thing.
ホント　部活とか勘弁な
Hey, Hachiken!
八軒…。　おーい。
Wake up, Hachi!
起きろ　ハチ！
"Hachi"?
「ハチ」？
Your alarm's too loud.
目覚まし　うるさい。
Chose a club yet?
部活　決めたか？
I think I wanna do martial arts.
俺　何か　武道やりてー。
How can these guys be so...
full of energy?
何で　こいつら
こんなにぴんぴんしてんだ？
What's wrong?
どうした？
Just feeling a bit dizzy...
ちょっと　目まいが。
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
Yeah, I'm okay.
うん…　平気。
Don't push yourself too hard.
無理しないでね。
I gotta tough it out!
頑張ろう！
I'm not the only one suffering!
しんどいのは俺一人じゃない！
Crap, I forgot to eat my morning snack.
チッ！
朝のおやつ食べるの忘れてきちゃったわ。
Episode 2
Hachiken
Rides a Horse
Yo, I know you guys are all tired,
おうおう！さすがに当番実習　終盤になると
now that we're approaching
the end of this practicum.
みんな　疲れが出てくるな。
Be careful!
気を付けろよ！
If you crack an egg,
you'll be suspended for a day!
卵１個　割ったら１日停学だからな。
Just kidding.
冗談だよ。
But that's just how careful
I want you guys to be.
けど　そんくらい気を付けろってことだ。
We're below livestock on
the ladder here, huh?
俺たちのヒエラルキーは家畜より下なんすね。
Below? Not even!
下どころではない！！
You guys are slaves to the livestock!
お前らは　家畜の奴隷だ！！
Slaves...
Campus Motto
Defy Logic  Cooperation  Diligence
I did it, Hachiken!
やったよ　八軒！
Because of you, I got a good
score on the math quiz!
数学の小テスト　お前のおかげでいい点取れたよー！
Oh?
That's great!
よかったな。
I got double-digits for
the first time ever!
人生初　数学で２桁！
What's with that score, after all the
detailed, personal tutoring I gave you?
何で　俺が　懇切丁寧にみっちり教えてやって
その点数なんだよぉ…。
Didn't I tell you not to
underestimate how stupid I am?
俺の頭　なめんなって言ったろ？
Sit down!
座れ！　また　一からみっちり　がっつり　教えてやる！！
I'm gonna drill it all into
you again, from square one!
Okay!
へーい。
Hachiken's amazing.
八軒　すげーな。
All right, we'll start with this problem.
He's not giving up on Tokiwa's brain.
あの常盤の頭にまだ付き合うとは　どうかしてるぜ。
Something's really wrong with him.
Next up is a class on raising crops.
次は　作物の外授業だぞ。
Hurry up and get changed!
We'll meet up on the fields!
早く着替えて　現場　行けー。
Those of you who haven't
indicated their club choices
まだ　部活希望　出してないやつ
have until the end of
next week to do so.
来週　締め切りだからな。
Make up your minds!
決めとけよ！
Okay!
うーっす。
Each of you gets 17 square meters!
１人当たり５坪くれてやる。　耕せー！
(10 AM): Practicum
Till it!
Twenty-one!
(2 PM): Physical Education
２１…　２２…。
Twenty-two!
After School (4 PM): Livestock Practicum
Off I go!
行ってくるぜ！
How the hell can anyone
どうやったら　これ以上部活なんて　できるんだよ…
Later (after 5 PM): Joining Club Practice Mid-Way
go to clubs after this?
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
Man, I sure worked hard today, too.
あ～　今日も働いたな～。
Yo!
よっ！
We've met you before.
この前の…。
Oh, we helped you catch those chickens.
鶏　捕まえるの手伝った…。
I'm Inada, a third-year
in food science.
食品科３年の稲田だ。
Thanks for your help the other day.
こないだは　どうもな。
I brought you guys the smoked
chicken, as promised!
約束のスモークチキン
持ってきたぞ！
I wanted you to try it
while it's still fresh!
出来たて　食わせてやりたくてさ。
Thank you for coming by
so late in the evening.
こんな遅くに
わざわざ　ありがとうございます。
You should eat it right away!
今すぐ　食べてみな。うまいぞ！
It's delicious!
Delicious!
うまいぞ！
No, stop that!
いやいやいや！
Don't make assumptions!
先入観はいかん！
Thanks for the food!
いただきます！！
Say something.
何とか言えよ。
んむ！　んむ！
Right?
だろ？
It tastes like...
there's nothing added to it.
何か…　余計なものが入ってない味がする。
You get it?!
分かるか？食品添加物使ってないんだよ　これ！
There are no additives in this!
Maybe you're made for food science!
お前食品科に向いてたんじゃないか？
You know what tastes good.
いい味覚してるよ。
I do?
そっすかね…。
I don't really get it.
よく分かんないっす。
Hey, Hachiken!
こら　八軒！
Don't eat all of it!
全部　食うな！
Let me have some, too!
俺にも食わせろよー。
あら　兄さん。
Oh, Brother.
Hey, Tamako.
おう　多摩子。
Are you still doing inefficient
research into additive-free foods?
相変わらず無添加食品なんて効率の悪い研究をやってるの？
This is an era of mass production
and mass consumption.
大量生産　大量消費の時代にはニーズに合わせて
You should accommodate the people's needs
添加物も上手に使っていくべきよ。
by making good use of additives.
"Brother"?
「兄さん」？
I'm gonna do things my way!
Smoked-Chicken Senpai and
Tamako are siblings?
スモークチキン先輩と多摩子ってきょうだいだったのか！
You keep your mouth shut.
Why not use them when they've
cleared safety regulations?
No way. They don't look anything alike.
嘘！？　似てないな。
They're not completely safe.
完全に安全ではないだろ。
Some don't even have
detectable levels...
研究数値も出てないものも…。
She'd be hot if she slimmed down!
トリミングしたら　美人だ～！！
Don't ever judge a book by its cover!
何事も　先入観で判断しない方が　よくってよ。
Komaba, a table's opened up.
駒場。台が空いたわ。
Play with me.
相手してちょうだい。
Okay!
Library
Recreation Room
Tamako, you're in the
table tennis club?
多摩子　卓球部なのか。
Wait, how can you have enough
energy left for that?
って　何でそんな体力が残ってるんだよ！
Table tennis has its own energy pool!
卓球は別腹です！
My killer move!
必殺…！
Monsters...
化け物どもめ…。
Chicken Coop
Clubs, huh?
部活かぁ…。
I have to pick one soon.
もう　決めないとな
Why not join the equestrian club?
馬術部に入らない？
Come check it out.
見学においでよ
Horses, huh?
馬か…。
Feed Store Room
(Biological Production Association: Practicum Room)
All right!
よーし。
You're done with the practicum!
今日の実習　終了！
Good work the past week!
１週間　お疲れー！
Yay!
やったー！
We won't have livestock practicum
for the rest of April, at least.
もう　４月いっぱいは畜産実習ないよね。
Thank God...
やったー！　しばらく朝５時起きから解放される！
I won't have to wake up
at five in the morning for a while!
But, clubs?
しかし　部活かぁ
I've barely done any sports, and that's
the only kind of clubs they have?
ろくに　スポーツしたことないのに運動部だけって…
And why must you join one when
there are so many practicums?
つーか　実習ありまくりなのに部活必須って…
Oh, man...
たまらんな～。
Nice...
たまりませんな～。
いいおっぱいしてんなー。
Nice tits.
I love the waistline of this one.
俺はこの腰のラインが…。
Excellent!
エクセレントですなー。
Oh, not bad...
おっとこれはまた…。
Super-excellent!
スーパーエクセレントですなー。
Aren't those too large?
ちょっと巨乳過ぎねえ？
あっ。
Who's there?!
誰だ！？
Oh, a first-year?
おう　１年か？何だよ？
What, don't hold back
if you're curious.
興味あるなら遠慮するなよ。
お前も見たいか？見たいだろ？
You want to see, too?
Of course you do.
Oh, well, uh...
えっ…。いや　その…。
I'll let you see, so just come.
見せてやっから　こっち来い。
Holstein Hall of Fame 2013
Aren't these great tits?!
いいおっぱいだろ！
Check out the great hip width!
絶妙な腰幅！
The balanced limbs!
四肢のバランス！
This is Bellwood-chan, last year's
champion in the forms category!
去年の体形審査チャンピオン
ベルウードちゃんだ！
What is this place?!
何なんすか　ここ！
The Ezonoo Holstein Club!
エゾノー　ホルスタイン部さ！
Holstein Club
We breed cows with beautiful form
and submit them to cattle fairs!
体形の美しい牛をつくり 品評会に出したりする
A club that loves Holsteins
above all others!
ホルスタインをこよなく愛する部だ！
Come join the Hol Club!
ホル部に入れよー！
Come make our dream woman together!
一緒に　好みの女をつくろうぜ。
No!
嫌だあああ！！
I don't want to spend my
high school years with
牛が恋人の白黒の高校生活なんて！！
a black-and-white cow as a girlfriend!
No!
嫌だあああぁぁ！！
Come now, Hol Club third-years.
これこれ！
ホル部３年生よ。
Don't terrorize a first-year.
１年生をいじめては　いけませんよ。
Let him go.
その子をお放しなさい。
Are you all right?
大丈夫ですか？
Oh... Thank you!
あぁ…ありがとうございます！
You appeared like an angel
rescuing me from hell...
地獄に仏とは　この…　こと…？
I am but a passing
equestrian club instructor.
通りすがりの馬術部顧問中島です。
My name is Nakajima.
If you are in need of help,
just say the word.
困ってることがあったら
言いなさい。
Ah, so you are looking
for the equestrian club?
何？馬術部を探しているとな。
I am just heading there, myself.
ちょうど私もそちらへ行くところです。
I will guide you there.
導いてあげましょう。
How can you not understand
the beauty of cows?
牛の美しさが分からんとは！
Forget human women!
人間の女なんぞ！
Do you even drink milk?
牛乳飲んでる？
Oh, it's Mikage.
御影だ。
Horses might be cool...
馬…カッコイイかも
This one's white and pretty, too.
この馬も真っ白で奇麗…
えっ！？じゃない！不細工！！
Nope!
Ugly!
You just thought this horse
looked ugly, didn't you?
君は今　この馬のことを不細工だと思いましたね。
Sorry.
すいません…。
Ow...
痛てて…。
You'll get yourself hurt
if you look down on them.
バカにしてると痛い目見るよ。
Horses are very observant of people.
馬は人をよく観察してるから。
You came to check us out.
見学 来てくれたんだ。ありがと！
Thanks!
Whoa! Is this the horse from before?
うわっ！この前の。
Yeah.
そうだよ　ニンジンあげてみる？
Want to give him a carrot?
Me?!
俺が！？
Hold it on your palm.
手のひらに載せて…。そうそう。
Yeah, like that.
Hold it on your palm.
手のひらに載せて…。そうそう。
Yeah, like that.
See? Aren't they cute?
ねっ　カワイイでしょ？
I don't know if I can call them that,
カワイイかどうかは分からないけど
but I've had enough lessons
over the past couple days to know
物事　先入観で判断してはいかんということは
that I can't make decisions
based solely on my assumptions!
ここ数日で嫌というほど学んだ！
Horses might look big and
scary at first glance,
馬ってさ　ぱっと見大きくて怖いかもしれないけど
but they're very timid and delicate.
とっても臆病で繊細なんだよ。
Seriously?
これで！？
Yeah.
うん。　自然界にないきらきら光るものや
They even get scared by shiny
things they don't see in nature,
and anything that flutters.
ひらひらしたものにおびえちゃうくらい。
Their shy nature also explains
why they're observant of people.
人をよく観察するっていうのは臆病の裏返し。
They're herbivores,
so they value the herd.
草食動物だから
基本　群れを大切にする。
They're shy, delicate,
and care about their kind.
臆病で　繊細で
仲間思いの動物なの。
They kind of sound like
a lot of trouble.
何か
めんどくさそうな生き物だな。
But isn't that what's
also good about them?
その　めんどくささがまた　いいっしょ？
I think you'd get along with them.
八軒君なら　きっと馬と　相性いいと思うんだ。
I encourage you to join
the equestrian club!
馬術部　お勧めするよ！
The equestrian club...
馬術部か…。
Riding around on a horse instead of using my legs
馬に乗って自分の足を使わないってのは
might make things easier...
楽でいいかもな…
Ooezo Agricultural High School Dormitory for Future Agriculture Managers
Club Registration Form
Equestrian Club
Class 1-D,
Hachiken Yuugo
Welcome to the equestrian club,
new students!
新入生の皆さん。
馬術部へ　ようこそ。
You'll be interacting with
live animals in this club,
生き物が相手の部活なので
初心者は大変だと思います。
so first-timers may find it tough.
Just ask upperclassmen and
people with more experience
分からないことは先輩や経験者にどんどん聞いてください。
if you have any questions.
The practicums are tough,
実習きついけど
but I'm off to a good
start with Mikage, too.
御影ともいい感じだし…
Maybe this high school isn't so bad.
農業高校
そんなに悪くないかもな
I don't have to wake up
at five anymore, either!
５時起きからも解放されたし！
By the way,
ちなみに　わが部は毎日馬の世話があるので
you'll need to take care
of the horses every day,
so you'll wake up every
morning at four.
毎朝４時起きです。
Oh, he's out cold.
あっ　倒れた。
You're slow, Mikage!
遅いぞ　御影！
Wait for me, Hachiken-kun!
待ってよ　八軒く～ん。
Yeah, right.
ああ　そうだよ！
I knew that wasn't gonna happen.
なんてことにはならないって分かってたよ！
First-year!
１年！
Hurry up and clean out the muck!
早く　ボロ　片付けとけよー！
I wonder when they'll let us ride one.
いつになったら馬に乗せてくれるんだろーな。
Man, this is an impressive
pile of manure.
しっかし
すごい　馬ふんの山だね～。
We've done nothing but muck stalls
since the day we joined.
俺ら　入部してから馬房の掃除しか　してねーべ。
But, thanks to that...
でも　おかげでさ…。
うん？
Man, breakfast is awesome
again today.
あ～！
今日も朝ご飯　超うめえ！
I wonder what's for lunch.
昼飯は　何が出るかな？
Crap, food is all I have
to look forward to!
飯だけが楽しみになってる！！
Gotcha!
隙あり。
You're starting to fit in, Hachi.
ここに染まってきたな　ハチよ。
Time for clubs!
部活　行こ。
Crap! I gotta go to the school kiosk!
ヤッベ！　購買　行かなきゃ。
I'm just gonna be mucking
stalls again, anyway.
どうせ　今日も　馬房掃除だよな。
What a drag.
しんどー。
Hachiken-kun!
八軒君！
Yeah?
ああ。
Going to your club?
部活　行くの？
Yeah.
うん。
So am I.
僕も。　方向　一緒だ。
Mine's in the same direction.
Which one did you choose?
何部　入った？
The Holstein Club.
ホルスタイン部。
I know what you're thinking.
言いたいことは分かるけどさ
But aside from the upperclassmen,
it's a proper club.
まともな部だよ　先輩以外は。
I appreciate being able to look
at livestock outside of classes.
授業以外でも家畜　見てられるってのは
ありがたいんだよ。
I see.
そっか。　獣医志望だもんな。
I guess you do want to become a vet.
But if you want to go to a vet school,
でも
そういう大学目指すんなら
wouldn't you normally
choose a high school
普通教科がっつりやる学校選ぶもんじゃないの？
that's strong in normal academics?
Normally, yeah.
普通はね。
Despite being a high school,
この学校　高校のくせに受精卵移植やクローン研究のできる設備があって
they have facilities for researching cloning
and transporting fertilized eggs.
They let you participate if you want.
希望者は参加できるんだよ。
I wanted to get that kind of
experience as soon as possible.
そういうのに　少しでも早く関わりたくて　ここを選んだんだ。
That's why I chose this school.
This school's amazing.
何か　すげーよ　この学校。
Everyone has a well-thought-out dream.
みんなしっかりした夢　持ってて。
As for me...
俺なんか…。
Even if you have a dream,
夢　持ってて
and know what you need to
make your dream come true,
かなえる方法　分かっててもさ
that's not enough.
それだけじゃ　駄目なんだ。
All right, my club room's this way.
じゃあ　僕　部室　こっちだから。
Good luck, Aikawa!
頑張れ　相川！
You're leaning forward.
前のめりになってますよ。
Okay!
はいっ。
When can I ride a horse
and look that cool?
いつんなったら　あんなふうに
カッコ良く乗れるのかなぁ
Wait, is that my dream?
あれ？　カッコ良く乗りたいってのは　夢なのかな？
I hurt all over.
全身　筋肉痛だし…。
Can they just let me
ride a horse already?
早く馬に乗せてくんないかな…。
It stinks.
くっせえ…。
Well, this might do the trick.
まあ　こんなもんでいっか。
It looks clean, right?
奇麗に…　見えるよな？
Yeah, it does!
見える見える！うん　バレない！
No one will find out!
Do you not like horses?
君。馬は好きじゃないの？
Huh?
はっ？
You're in the equestrian club, right?
馬術部員だよね？
Um... Yes, I am.
えっと…。部員ですけど。
You cut corners.
手抜き。
えっ？
You didn't join because
you liked horses?
馬が好きで入部したんじゃないの？
Well, um...
いや　その…。
When I joined, I was
just going with the flow.
流れで入部しちゃったっていうか…。
I'm sorry.
すいません。
Do you have no interest in horses?
馬に興味ないの？
えっ？　えーと…。
Um, well...
To be honest, I think just
being able to ride them is cool.
その…。　ぶっちゃけ　乗れたらカッコイイなーくらいで
馬自体は　苦手かもしんないです。
I might actually be
uncomfortable around horses.
That's fine.
それはよい！
Huh?
えっ？
You're a new student, no?
君。新入生だね。
Are you in Dairy Science?
酪農科だっけ？
I'm Hachiken, a first-year.
１年の八軒です。
Ah, you were a general applicant.
あぁ　一般で入った子か。
I find it curious that
you'd join Dairy Science
農家の子じゃないのに
酪農科に来るとは面白いね。
when you're not from a farm.
What kind of career
are you considering?
どんな進路を考えてるの？
あっ…　あの…　すいません。
Um... I'm sorry.
I actually don't have
any specific dream...
実は　特に夢がなくて…。
I'm really sorry.
ホント　すいません。
That's fine!
それは　よい！
What?!
ええっ！？
I'll enjoy working with you.
楽しみだねー。
What's with this guy?
何だ？このおっさん
Nakajima-sensei, I've come
to see my pretty horse.
中島先生。
カワイイ私の馬を見に来たよー。
Oh, Principal.
おや　校長先生。
New students, welcome to our school.
新入生の皆さん。
School Entrance Ceremony
入学　おめでとうございます
Oh.
He was so short,
I didn't see his face!
小さ過ぎて見えんかった！
Would all of you first-timers
like to try riding a horse?
初心者諸君。
そろそろ　馬に乗ってみますか？
All right!
よしっ！
Hachiken-kun, have you ever ridden one?
八軒君。　馬に乗ったことは？
Only that time when you
let me ride behind you.
この前　先生の後ろに乗せてもらったのが初めてです。
How was it?
どんな感じでした？
I thought I'd fall off
because I was so high up.
高くて落っこちそうで…
I was kind of scared.
ちょっとビビりました。
I see.
うん。
Then try him.
では　ここに。
What?! That one?
えっ！　この馬…。
Here.
It's all right.
大丈夫です。
He takes his job seriously.
仕事はきちんとする馬です。
Okay...
うわっ　やっぱ　高っ！
Whoa, this is so high.
You have poor posture!
姿勢が悪いですよ！
Keep your back straight!
背筋を伸ばして！
Okay!
はい。
More!
もっと！　まだ縮こまってます。
You're still hunched over.
Straighten your back.
背筋を伸ばして。
Okay!
は…　はい。
Not enough!
まだまだ！
Pretend you're arching your back!
えび反るくらいの気持ちで！！
More!
もっと！もっと！もっと！
もっと！！もっと！！
More!
Okay!
はいーっ！！
Isn't it great to have a high-up view?
目線　高くなると気持ちいいね！
Even though I'm high up,
高いのに…　地面とつながってる感じがする
I feel like I'm still
in contact with the ground.
There are things you can only learn
自分と違う種族
when you have
faced the unknown,
価値観　生まれ　育ち…。
be it a different species,
different values, or upbringing.
未知のものと出会ったからこそ得られるものがあります。
That is why we, as human beings,
ですから　われわれ人間は
appreciate these animals
一人では見ることのできないこの景色を見せてくれる家畜に感謝し
that allow us to see the view
we cannot see by ourselves,
and take care of them daily.
日々お世話をするのです。
Therefore,
なので　世話が面倒だとか
if anyone does not feel the need
to care for them properly
手抜きをするやからは
I'll shove him headfirst
into a manure pile.
馬ぐその山に頭からぶち込みますよ。
Okay.
はい…。
Next weekend will be the
start of Golden Week.
週末からゴールデンウイークに突入です。
About stable duty during break...
休み中の馬の世話ですが
担当予定だった大川君が家庭の事情で
Ookawa-kun was scheduled to handle it,
but a family emergency has come up.
出られなくなりました。
Sorry.
ごめん。
Is anyone else available?
代わりにやれる人はいませんか？
I'm going to visit relatives
on Honshuu with my family.
俺　本州の親戚んちに家族で行くんだ。
I don't think I can get
the dates changed.
ずらせないなぁ。
うちも　畑が…。
I have to help out on my farm.
Um, I'll do it.
あの…　俺　やります。
Oh, you will?
おお　やってくれますか。
Thank you, Hachiken-kun.
では　八軒君　お願いします。
Work together with Mikage-san.
御影さんと２人協力してやるように。
あっ。
All right, dismissed.
では　解散。
Thanks a bunch, Hachiken!
八軒。　助かったわ！
Oh, it's nothing.
いえ　いいっすよ。　俺　どうせ休み中　家に帰らないし。
I'm not going home
over break, anyway.
Okay!
そっか。
Thanks for taking care of
the horses over break!
休みの間　馬のこと　よろしくな！
Leave it to me, no matter
how many days!
任せてください　何日でも！
Man, I'm tired.
ハァ～　疲れた～。
I have very important information.
重大な情報がある。
Why so serious?
何だよ　もったいぶって。
この真上
The girls' bath is apparently
right above us.
女子の風呂らしいんだよね。
あっ？
A man's dream, eh?
男の夢…　だよな。
うん…。
Dream...
夢…
Hey, get out already!
おら　早く出ろ！次の班　入るぞ！
The next team's coming in!
Denied!
断る！！
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子はどうですか
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中で探しまわってた
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒に歌わないか
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日は頑張ろうぜ
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.